<!-- version: $Id$ -->

<page zone="IntAct" title="User Manual" format="column">

    <section title="Contents" name="cont">

        <auto-index index="main"/>

    </section>

    <division name="main" style="numbered">


        <section title="Introduction" name="intro">

            <blockquote>
                IntAct is a protein interaction database and analysis system. It provides a query interface and modules
                to analyse interaction data. This manual describes the IntAct data structure and the components of the
                IntAct system.
            </blockquote>

        </section>

        <section title="Recent changes" name="new">

            <blockquote>
                <u>Changes up to February 28, 2006</u>
                :
                <ul>
                    <li>New
                        <a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/intact/search/do/initAdvSearch">Advanced search</a>
                        added.
                    </li>
                    <li>New
                        <a href="#interpro.search">InterPro search</a>
                        added.
                    </li>
                    <li>In addition to the user manual, a dedicated
                        <a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/intact/doc/html/curation/IntActAnnotationRules.pdf">curation
                            manual</a>
                        has been released.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </blockquote>
            <blockquote>
                <u>Changes up to January 01, 2005</u>
                :
                <ul>
                    <li>New
                        <a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/intact/search">Search</a>
                        user interface available.
                    </li>
                    <li>New IntAct
                        <a href="./tutorial/index.html">API tutorial.</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>Integration of data including features (eg.
                        <a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/intact/search/do/hvWelcome?searchString=EBI-474155&amp;searchClass=Experiment&amp;source=simple">
                            Goehler et al.</a>
                        ).
                    </li>
                    <li>Integration of IntAct data into
                        <a href="http://www.ebi.uniprot.org/">UniProt</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>IntAct takes part in the
                        <a href="http://imex.sourceforge.net/">IMEx consortium</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>New application (
                        <a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/intact/mine">MiNe</a>
                        ) allowing to find the
                        minimal connecting network given a set of proteins.
                    </li>
                    <li>New application (
                        <a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/intact/targets">Targets</a>
                        ) to predict targets
                        for pull-down experiments.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </blockquote>
            <blockquote>
                <u>Changes up to February 01, 2004</u>
                :
                <ul>
                    <li>IntAct release 1: IntAct data is now available in
                        <a href="http://psidev.sf.net/mi/xml/doc/user/">PSI MI XML format</a>
                        , see the
                        <a href="#download">download</a>
                        section. Controlled vocabularies are available in GO DAG format.
                    </li>
                    <li>20672 interactions have been imported from Giot et al, 2003. The dataset contains extensive
                        crosslinking to UniProt, GO, InterPro, and FlyBase.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </blockquote>
        </section>

        <section name="data" title="Data">

            <section name="download" title="Download">
                <blockquote>IntAct data is available in
                    <a href="http://psidev.sf.net/mi/xml/doc/user/">PSI MI XML format</a>
                    .
                    Each IntAct release is split into multiple XML files according to the pattern Species_name-[small |
                    exeriment-name].xml. For example, s-cerevisiae_small.xml contains data on all small-scale
                    experiments
                    in S.cerevisiae stored in IntAct, s-cerevisiae_ho-2002.xml contains the data from the Ho et al,
                    2002 experiment. The current release is available at
                    <a href="ftp://ftp.ebi.ac.uk/pub/databases/intact/current/xml/">
                        ftp://ftp.ebi.ac.uk/pub/databases/intact/current/xml/</a>
                    .
                </blockquote>
            </section>
            <!-- end download -->

            <section name="CVS" title="Controlled Vocabularies">
                <blockquote>
                    To ensure data consistency, IntAct makes intensive use of controlled vocabularies.
                    All controlled vocabularies are available in Gene Ontology DAG-Edit format and HTML format.
                    Some IntAct annotation of controlled vocabulary terms do not fit the GO DAG-Edit format, but
                    as we want to export all available information, some comments might have to be filtered out from
                    the *.def files before editing them in GO DAG-Edit. For an overview and download of IntAct
                    controlled vocabularies, see
                    <a href="ftp://ftp.ebi.ac.uk/pub/databases/intact/current/cv/">
                        ftp://ftp.ebi.ac.uk/pub/databases/intact/current/cv/</a>
                    .
                </blockquote>
            </section>
            <!-- end CVS -->

            <section name="statistics" title="Statistics">
                Please see separate
                <a href="statistics/index.html">statistics section</a>
                .
            </section>
            <!-- end statistics -->

        </section>
        <!-- end data -->

        <section title="IntAct data representation" name="core">

            <section title="Common elements" name="CommonElements">

                <blockquote>
                    All main IntAct objects have the following attributes:
                </blockquote>

                <section title="ac" name="BasicObject.ac">

                    <blockquote>
                        The accession number. This is a unique, stable identifier for an object.
                        The same accession number will always be associated with the same object.
                        To reference IntAct objects from outside, accession numbers should be used.
                        The format of the accession number is one or more uppercase letters, followed by a dash,
                        followed by a number.
                        <br/>
                        In regular expression syntax: [A-Z0-9]+\-[0-9]+
                        <br/>
                        Example: EBI-15
                    </blockquote>

                </section>

                <section title="shortlabel" name="AnnotatedObject.shortLabel">

                    <blockquote>
                        The name is a short, concise name to identify an object.
                        Names for proteins are usually UniProt IDs,
                        names for experiments are usually:
                        <b>author-year-number</b>
                        .
                        <br/>
                        <b>author</b>
                        being the name of the first author of the associated publication.
                        That author name can be truncated if too long.
                        <br/>
                        <b>year</b>
                        being the year of the publication.
                        <br/>
                        <b>number</b>
                        maybe be used in case we create multiple experiments related to one publication.
                        <br/>
                        names for interactions are usually the name of gene1 'hyphen' name of gene2.
                        <br/>
                        Names will normally be stable, but they may change, e.g. when the gene name of a protein is
                        changed
                        by the relevant nomenclature body, e.g. HUGO. Names are not guaranteed to be unique,
                        e.g. if two proteins have the same primary gene name. They are guaranteed to be unique for
                        controlled vocabulary terms within each controlled vocabulary. All names are in lowercase.
                        <br/>
                        Example for a protein: got2_yeast.
                    </blockquote>

                </section>

                <section title="fullName" name="AnnotatedObject.fullName">

                    <blockquote>
                        The full name of the object.
                        <br/>
                        Example: Aspartate aminotransferase.
                    </blockquote>

                </section>

                <section title="Xref" name="AnnotatedObject.Xref">

                    <blockquote>
                        Crossreferences to other databases. A crossreference has the following attributes:
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                <b>Name</b>
                                :The name of the external database.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                <b>Primary id</b>
                                : The primary id or accession number of the object in the external database.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                <b>Secondary id</b>
                                : The secondary id of the object in the external database.
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                <a name="Xref.cvXrefType"></a>
                                <b>Crossreference type</b>
                                : The type of crossreference.
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </blockquote>

                </section>

                <section title="Annotation" name="AnnotatedObject.Annotation">

                    <blockquote>
                        Each object may have one or more annotations associated with it. Each annotation has a topic,
                        which broadly classifies the annotation, and the annotation text.
                    </blockquote>

                </section>

                <section title="created" name="BasicObject.created">

                    <blockquote>
                        The date the object has been created.
                    </blockquote>

                </section>

                <section title="updated" name="BasicObject.updated">

                    <blockquote>
                        The date the object has been updated last.
                    </blockquote>

                </section>

            </section>
            <!-- Common elements -->


            <section title="Main objects" name="mainObject">

                <blockquote>
                    IntAct has the following main objects:
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <a href="#Experiment">Experiment</a>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <a href="#Interaction">Interaction</a>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <a href="#Interactor">Interactor</a>
                        </li>
                    </ul>

                    <br/>

                    <a name="mainObjectsExample"></a>
                    Example (simplified): Representation of the Interleukin 2 receptor binding:
                    One interaction object represents the complex of the alpha, beta, and gamma chains which form the
                    receptor. This interaction object is then used in the second interaction object, in which the
                    binding
                    of Interleukin 2 to the receptor is represented. Both Interaction objects are linked to an
                    experiment,
                    in which the Interaction has been determined.
                    <img align="left" src="./images/core/intactMainObjects2.jpg" height="108" width="214"/>
                    <img align="right" src="./images/core/intactMainObjects.jpg" height="160" width="344"/>
                    <br clear="all"/>
                    The following section describes the main objects in detail.
                </blockquote>

                <section title="Experiment" name="Experiment">

                    <blockquote>
                        An Experiment object describes an experiment which has been performed to generate one or more
                        interactions. It indicates the conditions in which the experiment has been performed.
                        The description broadly classifies the experiment, it does not aim at providing all the
                        necessary data to repeat the experiment. The attributes of the Experiment are the
                        <dl>
                            <dt>
                                <a href="#BioSource">BioSource</a>
                            </dt>
                            <dd>The biological system in which the interaction took place in the experiment.</dd>

                            <dt>
                                <a name="Experiment.cvIdentification"></a>
                                identificationMethod
                            </dt>
                            <dd>The experimental method by which the molecules participating in the interaction have
                                been detected.
                                <br/>
                                Example: Mass spectrometry.
                            </dd>

                            <dt>
                                <a name="Experiment.cvInteraction"></a>
                                interactionMethod
                            </dt>
                            <dd>The experimental method by which the interaction has been detected.
                                <br/>
                                Example: yeast two hybrid.
                            </dd>
                        </dl>
                        Each Experiment provides a list of one or more
                        <a href="#Interaction">Interactions</a>
                        which have been determined by this Experiment. One Experiment might contain a single
                        Interaction, or many hundreds for large scale experiments.
                    </blockquote>

                </section>
                <!-- Experiment -->


                <section title="Interaction" name="Interaction">

                    <blockquote>
                        The Interaction object describes the interaction of two or more
                        <a href="#Interactor">Interactors</a>
                        (proteins). As the number of Interactors in an Interaction
                        is not limited, an Interaction can describe both binary interactions, which are the result of
                        for example yeast two hybrid experiments, and interactions with more than two Interactors, for
                        example determined by "TAP" experiments. The attributes of an Interaction are
                        <dl>
                            <dt>CvInteractionType</dt>
                            <dd>A description of the type of interaction.
                                <br/>
                                Example: association.
                            </dd>
                            <dt>kD</dt>
                            <dd>The dissociation constant.</dd>
                        </dl>
                    </blockquote>

                </section>
                <!-- Interaction -->


                <section title="Interactor" name="Interactor">

                    <blockquote>
                        A molecule or complex participating in an Interaction. The
                        only direct attribute of an Interactor is
                        <dl>
                            <dt>
                                <a href="#BioSource">BioSource</a>
                            </dt>
                            <dd>The biological system in which the interactor normally is found. For a human protein,
                                the BioSource would be "Human", even if it has been expressed in E.coli in a particular
                                experiment.
                            </dd>
                        </dl>
                        If the Interactor is a Protein, it additionally has the attributes
                        <dl>
                            <dt>sequence</dt>
                            <dd>The amino acid sequence of the protein.</dd>
                            <dt>crc64</dt>
                            <dd>The CRC64 checksum for the amino acid sequence. This checksum is used to quickly detect
                                if the amino acid sequence has changed, for example during an update process. It is also
                                used to check if the amino acid sequence has potentially been corrupted.
                                <br/>
                                The algorithm to compute the CRC64 is described in the ISO 3309 standard.
                                The generator polynomial is x64 + x4 + x3 + x + 1.
                                <br/>
                                Reference: Press W.H., Flannery B.P., Teukolsky S.A. and Vetterling W.T. "Numerical
                                recipes in C", 2nd ed., pp896-902, Cambridge University Press (1993). (See
                                http://www.ulib.org/webRoot/Books/Numerical_Recipes/bookcpdf/c20-3.pdf)
                                It should be noted that while, in theory, two different sequences could have the
                                same CRC64 value, the likelihood that this would happen is extremely low.
                            </dd>
                        </dl>
                        An Interactor describes an "abstract" form of e.g. a protein,
                        similar to a description in a protein sequence database. One
                        protein can participate in many interactions. To describe the
                        specific conditions in which an Interactor participates in an
                        Interaction, the following additional attributes are used:
                        <dl>
                            <dt>stoichiometry</dt>
                            <dd>The number of units of this interactor which participate in the interaction. The default
                                is one.
                            </dd>
                            <dt>expressedIn</dt>
                            <dd>A
                                <a href="#BioSource">BioSource</a>
                                object which describes the biological system in
                                which the protein has been expressed.
                                <br/>
                                Example: If a human protein has been expresed in E.coli, expressedIn would refer to
                                E.coli.
                            </dd>
                            <dt>Role</dt>
                            <dd>The role of the Interactor in the Interaction. In a yeast two hybrid experiment,
                                each Interaction would usually have an Interactor which has the role "bait" and another
                                one which has the role "prey".
                            </dd>
                            <dt>Features</dt>
                            <dd>The Features record the properties of the molecule that is involved in the interaction.
                            </dd>
                        </dl>

                        An Interactor is normally a protein. However, to model hierarchical assemblies of complexes
                        from subcomplexes, an Interactor can also be an Interaction.
                        <br/>
                        Example: To model a receptor-ligand interaction, the receptor could be modeled by an interaction
                        which describes the composition of the receptor from its component proteins. Then, in another
                        Interaction, the association of receptor and ligand would be described. See the
                        <a href="#mainObjectsExample">IL-2 example</a>
                        .
                        <br/>
                    </blockquote>

                </section>
                <!-- Interactor -->

            </section>
            <!-- Main objects -->


            <section title="Auxiliary objects" name="AuxiliaryObjects">

                <blockquote>
                    The following objects are auxiliary objects, often used in several different main classes.
                </blockquote>


                <section title="BioSource" name="BioSource">

                    <blockquote>
                        <dd/>
                        The BioSource object describes a biological system, usually a species. The attributes of a
                        BioSource are
                        <dl>
                            <dt>taxId</dt>
                            <dd>The NCBI tax id, see the
                                <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Taxonomy/">NCBI taxonomy server</a>
                                or the
                                <a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/newt">NEWT taxonomy server</a>
                                .
                                <br/>
                                <u>Technical note</u>
                                : We are using a programatical access to the Newt server to create on-the-fly
                                new BioSources in IntAct.
                            </dd>
                            <dt>shortLabel</dt>
                            <dd>The shortLabel is the UniProt OS code, where available.</dd>
                            <dt>fullName</dt>
                            <dd>The full name is the scientific name of the species.</dd>
                            <dt>tissue
                                <font color="gray">(optional)</font>
                            </dt>
                            <dd>The tissue is the tissue type used in the experiment.</dd>
                            <dt>compartment
                                <font color="gray">(optional)</font>
                            </dt>
                            <dd>The compartment is the cellular compartment in which the interaction has been shown to
                                occur.</dd>
                            <dt>cell type
                                <font color="gray">(optional)</font>
                            </dt>
                            <dd>The cell type is the cell line in which the interaction is shown to occur.</dd>
                        </dl>
                    </blockquote>

                </section>
                <!-- BioSource -->

                <section title="CvObject" name="CvObject">

                    <blockquote>
                        IntAct makes intensive use of controlled vocabularies. Where
                        possible, data attributes are controlled vocabularies, the
                        terms are selected from a defined list instead of being free
                        text. For each attribute which is selected from a controlled
                        vocabulary, a specific CvXXXXX class exists, for example
                        CvInteractionType. Each term in a controlled vocabulary has a
                        definition, usually has crossreferences, and may have
                        additional comments.
                    </blockquote>

                </section>
                <!-- CvObject -->

                <!-- TODO name to be updated -->
                <section title="Features" name="FEATURES_HELP_SECTION">

                    <blockquote>
                        The attributes of the individual protein molecules involved in the
                        interaction are recorded as features of the proteins. This includes
                        information such as the range of amino acids involved in the interaction,
                        tagging of the protein molecule, mutations in the sequence etc.
                        <br/>
                        Controlled
                        vocabulary is used for determining the feature type and feature
                        identification method. The features are then displayed in search as an
                        autogenerated sentence. Additional crossreferences in the features also
                        give information about the structure and domains in the proteins.
                    </blockquote>

                </section>
                <!-- CvObject -->

            </section>
            <!-- Auxiliary objects -->

        </section>
        <!-- IntAct data representation -->


        <section title="IntAct applications" name="IntAct-applications">

            IntAct provides a number of applications. Depending on the installation you are using, some modules
            described here may not be available, or additional modules not described in this manual might be available.

            <section title="Search" name="search">

                <section title="Availability" name="search.availability">

                    <blockquote>
                    </blockquote>

                </section>

                <section title="External linking to IntAct" name="external.linking">

                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <b>general search</b>
                            <br/>
                            <p>
                                http://www.ebi.ac.uk/intact/search/do/search?searchString=
                                <b>
                                    <font color="blue">&lt;query.string&gt;</font>
                                </b>
                                <!--[&searchClass=<b><font color="red">&lt;object.name&gt;</font></b>]-->
                            </p>
                            <b>
                                <font color="blue">&lt;query.string&gt;</font>
                            </b>
                            is the user query that the searched object should match.
                            <br/>
                            Wildcards are supported.
                            <br/>
                            it can be either:
                            <ul>
                                <li>AC</li>
                                <li>shortlabel</li>
                                <li>fullname</li>
                                <li>Xref (UniProt, GO, FlyBase, SGD, Interpro...)</li>
                                <li>Alias (gene name, locus, orf ...)</li>
                            </ul>
                            <br/>

                        </li>

                        <li>
                            <b>Known partners of a protein</b>
                            <br/>
                            <p>
                                http://www.ebi.ac.uk/intact/search/do/search?searchString=
                                <b>
                                    <font color="blue">&lt;protein&gt;</font>
                                </b>
                            </p>
                            <b>
                                <font color="blue">&lt;protein&gt;</font>
                            </b>
                            should be either the AC, shortlabel,
                            alias or Xref (eg. UniProt ID) of a Protein.
                            <br/>
                            Wildcards are supported.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                        </li>

                        <li>
                            <b>Binary interactions</b>
                            <br/>
                            <p>
                                http://www.ebi.ac.uk/intact/search/do/search?binary=
                                <b>
                                    <font color="red">&lt;protein1&gt;</font>
                                </b>
                                ,
                                <b>
                                    <font color="blue">&lt;protein2&gt;</font>
                                </b>
                            </p>
                            This URL will give you all the binary interactions for two given proteins contained within
                            IntAct.
                            There are cases when
                            <b>
                                <font color="red">&lt;protein1&gt;</font>
                            </b>
                            and
                            <b>
                                <font color="blue">&lt;protein2&gt;</font>
                            </b>
                            will be the same, for example in the case of a homodimer or when an interaction is
                            demonstrated between different modified forms of the same protein (e.g. Flag-tagged and
                            wild-type).
                            <br/>
                            <b>
                                <font color="red">&lt;protein1&gt;</font>
                            </b>
                            and
                            <b>
                                <font color="blue">&lt;protein2&gt;</font>
                            </b>
                            should be either the AC, shortlabel, alias or Xref (eg. UniProt ID) of a Protein.
                            <br/>
                            Wildcards are supported but we encourage you to give a specific protein descriptor.
                        </li>

                    </ul>

                </section>


                <section title="Basic Overview" name="search.Overview">

                    <blockquote>
                        The search application currently allows a text-based search by entering
                        a text string into the search text box. It is possible to obtain information
                        on experiments, protein interactions, the proteins themselves and the controlled vocabulary
                        , with various views used to display the data. Intact uses the concept of
                        <a href="#AnnotatedObject.shortLabel">shortlabel</a>
                        which is intended to provide a way
                        of 'more memorable identification' compared to an
                        <a href="#BasicObject.ac">accession number (ac)</a>
                        , although searches by ac are
                        obviously allowed. For example a particular Experiment may have an ac of
                        EBI-12, but its name is 'gavin-2002' indicating a more meaningful reference
                        to the physical experiment which the entry represents. Basic points on
                        usage:

                        <ul>
                            <ul>
                                <li>
                                    Wildcard searching is supported - for example matches will be retrieved
                                    for strings such as EBI*, *BI-14, E*4, etc etc. Though if too many result
                                    match your expression, you will be given some statistics about how many
                                    objects have matched your query and you will be asked to refine your query.
                                    cf.
                                    <a href="#too.many.results">screenshot</a>
                                    .
                                </li>

                                <li>
                                    upper or lower case strings are acceptable (but not mixed case) and will be matched
                                    if they exist. The exception to this is a search by alias (ie gene name, as defined
                                    in UniProt) - currently these are stored as lower case and are searched for as such.
                                    This will become more sophisticated as the project matures.
                                </li>

                                <li>
                                    currently searches are looking for four main types of objects: experiment,
                                    interaction,
                                    protein, and controlled vocabulary term (that has many sub types).
                                    <br/>
                                    A search doesn't progress in a certain order as it used to be, we perform a global
                                    search on all mentionned types and if several of them match your query, a summary
                                    page will be displayd to give you an overview. That way, you can select the object
                                    you want to see amongst many types. cf
                                    <a href="#multi.types.result">screenshot</a>
                                    .
                                </li>

                                <li>
                                    At a lower level, specific attributes are searched by
                                    <a href="#BasicObject.ac">AC</a>
                                    ,
                                    <a href="#AnnotatedObject.shortLabel">shortlabel</a>
                                    ,
                                    <a href="#AnnotatedObject.fullname">fullname</a>
                                    <a href="#AnnotatedObject.Xref">Xref</a>
                                    (Uniprot AC, GO, SGD, FlyBase, Interpro...),
                                    and finally
                                    <a href="#AnnotatedObject.Annotation">alias</a>
                                    (gene, locus and orf name).
                                </li>

                                <li>
                                    Note that whilst controlled vocabulary term (also called CvObject) details can be
                                    displayed via the click of a link, currently it is not possible to search for
                                    CvObjects via the text box search entry point.
                                </li>
                            </ul>
                        </ul>
                    </blockquote>

                </section>
                <!--  -->

                <section title="Structure of Search Results" name="search.TableLayout">

                    <blockquote>
                        The basic layout of the main results page follows the structure below:

                        <br/>

                        <p>
                            <a NAME="experiment.single.view"></a>
                            An example result screen when searching for an Experiment
                            is shown below:
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <img SRC="./images/search/exp.png" border="0"/>
                        </p>

                        <p>
                            <a NAME="experiment.single.chunked"></a>
                            An other example result screen when searching for
                            an Experiment, this time there are too many interactions to display it in one go.
                            So, the Experiment is splited in several pages that you can reach using the index above
                            the Experiment.
                            <br/>
                            This is shown below:
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <img SRC="./images/search/exp-chunked.png" border="0"/>
                        </p>

                        <p>
                            <a NAME="interaction.single.view"></a>
                            An example result screen when searching for an Interaction is shown below, as you can see
                            the interaction is shown in the context of its experiment:
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <img SRC="./images/search/int_single.png" border="0"/>
                        </p>

                        <p>
                            <a NAME="too.many.results"></a>
                            An example result screen when submiting a query that matches too many results, we show some
                            basic statistics:
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <img SRC="./images/search/too_many_results.png" border="0"/>
                        </p>

                        <p>
                            <a NAME="multi.types.result"></a>
                            An example result screen when submiting a query that matches different types of objects,
                            if there are not too many of them, we show simpler version of them to allow the user to
                            choose:
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <img SRC="./images/search/query_multi_obj.png" border="0"/>
                        </p>

                        <p>
                            <a NAME="binary.view"></a>
                            Protein views can be of various types. Searching for a protein will result in a so-called
                            'binary view'. This view shows the list of proteins which are in a pairwise interaction
                            with the searched-for protein.
                            <a NAME="number.interactions"></a>
                            <p>
                                The column "number of interactions" indicates:
                                <br/>
                                a) for the query protein (first row), in how many distinct interactions it has been
                                observed.
                                <br/>
                                b) for all interactors of the query protein (subsequent rows), in how many interactions
                                the
                                current protein (current row) and the query protein (first row) interact.
                            </p>

                            An example result screen for this view is shown below:
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <img SRC="./images/search/binary.png" border="0"/>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <a NAME="interaction.details.view"></a>
                            Viewing the interactions involved for a particular (couple of) protein can also be done
                            from the binary view by clicking on the interaction count.
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <a NAME="protein.single.view"></a>
                            The details for an individual protein are displayed as below:
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <img SRC="./images/search/protein_single.png" border="0"/>
                        </p>
                        <br/>

                        <p>
                            <a NAME="single.view"></a>
                            If for example in the above screen you click on 'UniProt', this will display the controlled
                            vocabulary information for the database identified with a name of 'UniProt'. The screen
                            looks
                            like this:
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <img SRC="./images/search/uniprot.png" border="0"/>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <u>Note</u>
                            : You can see on that view that the CvDatabase called UniProt has been annotated
                            using Xref, some of them have a special role in the IntAct framework:
                            <ul>
                                <li>
                                    <b>search-url</b>
                                    : is used to forward to the original source of the object.
                                    In the case of 'UniProt', if a protein has such a Uniprot Xref attached, the search
                                    application would automatically generate a link to allow you to view that same
                                    protein on the UniProt web site.
                                    <br/>
                                    <u>eg</u>
                                    . Let
                                    <b>search-url</b>
                                    of the CvDatabase 'UniProt' be
                                    <b>http://www.ebi.uniprot.org/entry/${ac}</b>
                                    <br/>
                                    Let the primaryId of that Xref be
                                    <b>
                                        <font color="red">P12345</font>
                                    </b>
                                    , the search
                                    interface would replace ${ac} by
                                    <b>
                                        <font color="red">P12345</font>
                                    </b>
                                    and the URL
                                    in the search application would show up as:
                                    http://www.ebi.uniprot.org/entry/
                                    <b>
                                        <font color="red">P12345</font>
                                    </b>
                                    <br/>
                                </li>

                                <li>
                                    <b>search-url-ascii</b>
                                    : is used for programatical access to that database.
                                    In the case of UniProt, if a protein has such a Uniprot Xref attached, we can then
                                    get
                                    the UniProt FlatFile content correcponding to that protein.
                                    <br/>
                                    <u>eg</u>
                                    . Let
                                    <b>search-url-ascii</b>
                                    of the CvDatabase 'UniProt' be
                                    <b>http://www.ebi.uniprot.org/entry/${ac}?format=text&amp;ascii</b>
                                    <br/>
                                    Let the primaryId of that Xref be
                                    <b>
                                        <font color="red">P12345</font>
                                    </b>
                                    , the search
                                    interface would replace ${ac} by
                                    <b>
                                        <font color="red">P12345</font>
                                    </b>
                                    and the URL
                                    in the search application would show up as: http://www.ebi.uniprot.org/entry/
                                    <b>
                                        <font color="red">P12345</font>
                                    </b>
                                    ?format=text&amp;ascii
                                </li>
                            </ul>
                        </p>
                        <br/>
                        <p>
                            <a name="ShortLabelHelp"></a>
                            Protein names are links you can click to get a view of the protein details. Also each
                            protein name has a term in superscript which denotes the role that the protein plays in the
                            interaction. These terms have tooltips associated with them to display the role name, and
                            also the term is a clickable link from which you can view the full details of the controlled
                            vocabulary term which presents the controlled vocabulary information for that term (eg the
                            details held to define the meaning of the term 'bait').
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            Since the items displayed for a search result include many items not actually queried for,
                            the items that matched the original search string are
                            <b>
                                <font color="red">highlighted in
                                    red</font>
                            </b>
                            . Specifically the *names* of the matching items are
                            highlighted, since these are always displayed in every view.
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            Where a protein (for example) might actually occur more than once in an experiment, the
                            display is rationalised to avoid multiple presentations of the same experiment - therefore
                            all occurrences within an experiment are gathered together into one experiment view.</p>
                        <p>
                            <a NAME="ButtonDefinition"></a>
                            At the bottom of the page are a number of buttons:
                        </p>
                        <ul>
                            <ul>

                                <li>
                                    a
                                    <b>Graph</b>
                                    button to display a graph of any selected proteins or interactions,
                                    which can be chosen by clicking the appropriate checkboxes.
                                </li>

                                <li>
                                    a
                                    <b>Path</b>
                                    button to compute the minimal connecting network (using
                                    <a href="#mine">MiNe</a>
                                    ) of the set of protein you have selected using the tickboxes.
                                    It then displays a graph (using
                                    <a href="#hierarchView">hierarchView</a>
                                    ) showing
                                    the computed path. The computed path is highlighted by coloring the interaction in
                                    red along the path.
                                </li>

                                <li>a
                                    <b>Interpro</b>
                                    button to show the InterPro domain architecture for selected Proteins (using
                                    <a href="#interpro.search">InterProSearch</a>
                                    ).
                                </li>


                                <li>a
                                    <b>Select all</b>
                                    button to check all tickboxes.
                                </li>

                                <li>a
                                    <b>Clear all</b>
                                    button to uncheck all tickboxes.
                                </li>


                            </ul>
                        </ul>

                    </blockquote>

                </section>
                <!-- Basic Overview -->

                <section title="Advanced Search" name="advancedSearch">
                    <section title="Access" name="advancedSearch.access">
                        <blockquote>
                            The URL to access the editor is dependent upon the server where the editor is installed.
                            The general format to access the editor takes the form of:
                            http://server/intact/search/do/initAdvSearch.
                        </blockquote>
                    </section>

                    <section title="Basic overview" name="advancedSearch.basicOverview">
                        <blockquote>
                            <p>
                                Before going into any further details you should notice that the AdvancedSearch page is
                                vertically
                                split within two parts. On the left hand side there is the real advancedSearch where you
                                can define
                                your request. On the right hand side there is a relevant example to help you using the
                                advancedSearch :
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/search/advancedSearch1.png" title=""/>
                                <br/>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                The advanced Search permits you to search for a specific object thus to choose what you
                                want to
                                see in your result page. Here are the objects you can ask for :
                                <ul>
                                    <li>Controlled Vocabulary Term</li>
                                    <li>Experiment</li>
                                    <li>Interaction</li>
                                    <li>Protein</li>
                                </ul>
                                You can also search for any object.
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                After selecting which object you are searching for, you define the creterii which will
                                be used for
                                the request. Depending on the object you choosed to display and on your desire, you can
                                define 1 or
                                several of the following fields :
                                <ul>
                                    <li>The Accession Number</li>
                                    <li>The Short Label</li>
                                    <li>The Description</li>
                                    <li>A crossresference to an other database</li>
                                    <li>An annotation topic</li>
                                    <li>The method used to determine the interaction (Interaction detection, for
                                        Experiment only)</li>
                                    <li>The method used to determine the participants in the interaction (Participant
                                        detection, for Experiment only)</li>
                                    <li>The interaction type (for Interaction only)</li>
                                </ul>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                <a NAME="advancedSearch.basicOverview.criteriaCombination"></a>
                                If you decide to define several of the fields (ex : Accession Number and Description)
                                you can tell
                                the advanced Search whether you want the objects to match all the define fields or only
                                one of the
                                fields in selecting either &quot;all of the above (and)&quot; box or &quot;any of the
                                above (or)&quot; box.
                            </p>
                        </blockquote>
                    </section>

                    <section title="Structure of Advanced Search result" name="advancedSearch.result">
                        <blockquote>
                            <p>
                                If you choose to display any object you will obtain the same page then if you were doing
                                a normal search :
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/search/advancedSearch2.png" title=""/>
                                <br/>
                            </p>

                            <p>
                                If you choosed to display Controlled Vocabularies Term, the result page will follow the
                                structure below:
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/search/advancedSearch3.png" title=""/>
                                <br/>
                            </p>

                            <p>
                                If you choosed to display Experiments, the result page will follow the structure below:
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/search/advancedSearch4.png" title=""/>
                            </p>

                            <p>
                                <br/>
                                If you choosed to display Interactions, the result page will follow the structure below:
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/search/advancedSearch5.png" title=""/>
                                <br/>
                            </p>

                            <p>
                                If you choosed to display Proteins, the result page will follow the structure below:
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/search/advancedSearch6.png" title=""/>
                                <br/>
                            </p>
                        </blockquote>
                    </section>
                </section>
                <!-- Advanced Search -->

                <section title="InterPro Search" name="interpro.search">
                    <section title="Basic Overview" name="interpro.search.basic.overview">
                        <blockquote>
                            The following paragraph explains how to link from IntAct to InterPro to visualise
                            the protein domain architecture of IntAct proteins.
                            <br/>
                            Within the IntAct search interface, proteins and interactions can be selected by clicking
                            the relevant tickbox.
                            <br/>
                            If an interaction is selected, all participating proteins will be considered selected.
                            Once a protein set has been selected, the "InterPro" button on the top or bottom of
                            the page can be clicked.
                        </blockquote>

                    </section>
                    <!-- Basic Overview -->
                    <section title="Example of Use" name="interpro.search.example.of.use">
                        <blockquote>
                            The IntAct Search Page with red circles around a tickbox and the InterPro button.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/search/intact_red.png" title=""/>
                            <br/>
                            <br/>

                            After a short waiting time,
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/search/interpro1.png" title=""/>
                            <br/>
                            <br/>

                            you will then be forwarded to the InterPro page showing the domain architecture
                            for the selected proteins.

                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/search/interpro2.png" title=""/>
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/search/interpro3.png" title=""/>
                            <br/>
                            <br/>

                        </blockquote>
                    </section>
                    <!-- Example of Use -->
                </section>
                <!-- InterPro Search -->
            </section>
            <!-- Search -->


            <section title="Editor" name="editor">


                <section title="Overview" name="editor.overview">

                    <blockquote>
                        The editor is a web based tool to edit objects in the IntAct database.
                    </blockquote>

                </section>
                <!-- Overview -->


                <section title="Availability" name="editor.availability">

                    <blockquote>
                        The application to edit IntAct database is only available for
                        users with
                        <b>write</b>
                        access to it.
                    </blockquote>

                </section>


                <section title="Access" name="editor.access">

                    <blockquote>
                        The URL to access the editor is dependent upon the server where the
                        editor is installed. The general format to access the editor takes the
                        form of:
                        <br/>
                        http://server/intact[test|prod]/editor, where the server part may contain a port
                        depending upon the configuration of the web server. For example,
                        http://www.ebi.ac.uk/interpro/internal-tools/intacttest/editor
                        is the URL to access the internal EBI test editor. The purpose of the test version
                        is for testing and is shown in different color scheme to distinguish
                        it from the production version. All the figures in this document refers to the
                        color scheme of the production editor.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        To use the editor, you must have a valid account to access the Intact
                        database. The user is presented with a login screen as shown below:
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        <img src="./images/editor/login.png" title="" alt="Login Screen"/>
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        Failure to login with a valid account results in the following error
                        display:
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        <img src="./images/editor/login-error.png" title="" alt="Login error"/>
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        The user is presented with the following screen after a successful login:
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        <img src="./images/editor/login-success.png" title="" alt="Login Success"/>
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        In the bottom left corner of the above screen, shows the login name (smudali)
                        and the database (zpro) the editor is using. The footer shows the last modified
                        date (usually, the build date).
                    </blockquote>

                </section>
                <!-- Access -->


                <section title="IntAct Types" name="editor.intact.types">

                    <blockquote>
                        This list defines the types available for edit. Before proceeding with
                        any action (search or create), you must select an appropriate type
                        first.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        <img src="./images/editor/types.png" title="" alt="IntAct Types"/>
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        <img src="./images/editor/warning.gif" title="" alt="" align="left"/>
                        The IntAct type list defaults to the first item (i.e., Experiment) if a type wasn't selected.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                    </blockquote>

                </section>
                <!-- IntAct Types -->


                <section title="Search" name="editor.search">

                    <blockquote>
                        The user must select the type to edit from the drop down list.
                        The input field next to the Search button accepts the search criteria.
                        <br/>
                        The search is performed in the following order:
                        <ol>
                            <li>accession number (ac)</li>
                            <li>short label</li>
                            <!--                            <li>primary id</li>-->
                            <!--                            <li>full name</li>-->
                        </ol>
                        <img src="./images/editor/idea.gif" title="" alt="" align="left"/>
                        So, it is faster to search by an accession number than by a shortlabel.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        You can accept the default search value (*) by simply clicking on the
                        search button. This pratice is discouraged
                        <b>strongly</b>
                        as it may retrieve a large number
                        of records from the database for some types (i.e., Interaction). Instead, you should
                        use more restrictive filtering such as EBI-3* to retrieve a subset of
                        records.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        <img src="./images/editor/idea.gif" title="" alt="" align="left"/>
                        Fo faster response, always prefer a restrictive search criteria.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        An example for a successful search:
                        <br/>
                        <img src="./images/editor/results.png" title="" alt="Results page"/>
                        <br/>
                        The 'AC link' (see above) links the editor with the search application. The following
                        figure shows the result of clicking on EBI-39 link.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        <img src="./images/editor/search-link.png" title="Result of clicking on EBI-39 link"
                             alt="Search Link"/>
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        The 'shortlabel link', takes you to the appropriate edit screen. In this example,
                        'go' entry will be opened in the CV editor (see below, Cv Editors, for more on CV editor).
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        <img src="./images/editor/idea.gif" title="" alt="" align="left"/>
                        Alternatively, you can go to the edit screen by searching for EBI-39 or 'go' alone.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        A message will be displayed if a search fails to find any matching records.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        <img src="./images/editor/search-error.png" title="" alt="No Match"/>
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                    </blockquote>

                </section>
                <!-- Search -->


                <section title="Cv Editors" name="editor.cv.editors">

                    <blockquote>
                        The create button creates a record for the selected IntAct type. As
                        with the search, it is important to select the appropriate type before
                        clicking on the create button. The following screen shows the result of
                        creating a new CvDatabase record.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        <img src="./images/editor/new-cv.png" title="" alt="New CvDatabase"/>
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                    </blockquote>

                    <section title="Names" name="editor.short.labels">

                        <blockquote>
                            The current edit type is appended to the main heading (CvDatabase) as
                            shown above. All the drop down list items (topic, database and
                            reference qualifier) are shown in their shortlabels. Except for the
                            shortlabel, all other fields are optional. To distinguish between
                            required and optional fields, required fields are shown in a different
                            background colour. These fields are validated when the user selects
                            a button (i.e., Add Annotation, Save etc) on the page.
                            <br/>
                            All shortlabels should be one to
                            twenty characters from the character set blank, 0..9, a-z, : ',' (colon), '_' (underscore)
                            and
                            '-' (hyphen). A dialog box similar to the following will appear for a
                            failure to adhere to this syntax. Short labels are unique for all the editors apart for
                            the Feature editor. The editor by default computes a unique shortlabel from a given
                            value. For example, if 'abc' arleay exists on the database, giving 'abc' as
                            a short label defaults to abc-1.
                            <b>ADD THE link to the curation manual</b>
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/editor/shortlabel-client-error.png" title="" alt="Incorrect shortlabel"/>
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            Submitting the form without entering a syntactically valid name
                            could result in a server side validation if JavaScript is disabled in the client
                            browser. The error response from the server
                            is shown under the shortlabel (Note: this error only
                            appears if Javascript is disabled in the browser).
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/editor/shortlabel-server-error.png" title=""
                                 alt="Shortlabel server validation"/>
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            Although both validations are similar in nature, they serve two
                            different purposes. The first validation is performed on the client side
                            (browser) and hence faster of the two. However, the browser must be
                            enabled to accept Javascript for it to work (no dialog window if
                            Javascript is not enabled). This is the preferred validation as it saves
                            extra step in communicating with the server. Alternatively, the other
                            validation is not dependent on Javascript and hence works on
                            any browser.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/editor/warning.gif" title="" alt="" align="left"/>
                            However, some editor components such as Experiment and
                            Interaction editors rely on Javascript and they wouldn't work correctly
                            if Javascript is disabled. You will have then to enable Javascript in order to get
                            the Editor to work correctly.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                        </blockquote>

                    </section>
                    <!-- Names -->


                    <section title="Annotations" name="editor.annotations">

                        <blockquote>
                            Annotations are added by clicking on the Add Annotation button in the Annotation
                            section. Associated with each Annotation is a topic which is one of
                            CvTopics available in the database. An error message is displayed when
                            adding an annotation without selecting a type from
                            the drop down list first.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/editor/annotation-error.png" title="" alt="Annotation error"/>
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            The editing of an annotation is similar to adding a new Annotation except
                            for topic and description are already set to their existing values. The
                            annotations in the editing mode are shown in a different color to distinguish
                            them from non editing annotations.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/editor/edit-annotation.png" title="" alt="Editing an Annotation"/>
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/editor/warning.gif" title="" alt="" align="left"/>
                            You cannot save the form if an annotation is in 'edit' mode. In this case, you
                            must either save or delete it first.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/editor/idea.gif" title="" alt="" align="left"/>
                            Edit one annotation at a time as there is no way to save a group of
                            annotations in a single button click.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                        </blockquote>

                    </section>
                    <!-- Annotations -->


                    <section title="Crossreferences" name="editor.xrefs">

                        <blockquote>
                            Similar to Annotations, Crossreferences are added by clicking on the
                            Add Crossreference button in the Crossreference section. The database drop list
                            consists of names for CvDatabase items from the IntAct database and
                            the reference qualifier consists of names for CvXrefQualifier.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/editor/add-xref.png" title="Adding a new Xref" alt="New Xref"/>
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            As with annotations, the values from drop down lists must be selected
                            prior to adding a crossreference. Editing an existing Crossreference
                            is similar to adding a new one except for existing values are shown instead
                            of empty values.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/editor/warning.gif" title="" alt="" align="left"/>
                            Any changes to the form are not saved until the form is submitted. So
                            for a new IntAct type, a record is not created on the database until the
                            Submit or Save &amp; Continue button is clicked and the server reports no errors.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/editor/idea.gif" title="" alt="" align="left"/>
                            Save your work periodically by selecting Save &amp; Continue. This avoids the
                            danger of loosing your data due to an extended period of inactivity (session
                            timing out).
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            Editing an existing record is similar to the above except the form is
                            populated with existing data. As shown below, the name and full
                            name already have their existing values.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/editor/edit-cv.png" title="Editing an existing entry"
                                 alt="Editing an existing CV object"/>
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                        </blockquote>

                    </section>
                    <!-- Crossreferences -->

                </section>
                <!-- Cv Editors -->


                <section title="Other Editors" name="editor.other.editors">

                    <blockquote>
                        Since Cv editor layout is common to all the other editors, only the
                        differences are shown for them.
                    </blockquote>

                    <section title="BioSource" name="editor.biosource">

                        <blockquote>
                            The biosource editor uses the Newt server to auto-complete the short
                            label and the full name from a given NCBI taxid.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <img src="./images/editor/new-biosrc.png" title="New BioSource"
                                 alt="Biosource editor"/>
                        </blockquote>

                    </section>
                    <!-- BioSource -->


                    <section title="Experiment" name="editor.experiment">

                        <blockquote>
                            <img src="./images/editor/new-exp.png" title=""
                                 alt="New Experiment"/>
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            The Host Organism is the organism the experiment has been performed in. Example: If the
                            interaction of Human proteins expressed in E.coli has been studied in Yeast, the Host
                            Organism would be Yeast.
                            The Interaction Detection describes the method which has been used to detect the
                            interaction, e.g. yeast two hybrid.
                            The Participant Detection describes the method which has been used to detect the
                            participants (proteins) involved in the interaction, e.g. peptide mass fingerprinting.
                        </blockquote>

                    </section>
                    <!-- Experiment -->


                    <section title="Interaction" name="editor.interaction">

                        <blockquote>
                            <img src="./images/editor/interaction.jpg" title="Interaction Editor"
                                 alt="Interaction Editor"/>
                        </blockquote>

                        <section title="Experiments" name="editor.int.experiments">

                            <blockquote>
                                This section describes Experiments already part of the current
                                Interaction. The area below holds experiments not yet added to the
                                Interaction as shown below.
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/editor/int-exp.png" title="" alt="Experiments not yet added"/>
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                Select Add button to add an experiment or Hide to remove from the
                                collection. Duplicate experiments are not allowed.
                            </blockquote>

                        </section>
                        <!-- Experiments -->

                        <section title="Proteins" name="editor.int.proteins">

                            <blockquote>
                                This section lists all the Proteins participating in the current
                                Interaction. For a new Interaction, this section is empty. To add a
                                Protein, you must search for existing Proteins first by providing
                                appropriate values for search fields. Only the most specific value
                                is taken into consideration if multiple values are provided for search.
                                Since IntAct AC is the most specific, other search values are ignored
                                if a value was specified for IntAct AC.
                                <br/>
                                If a search is performed by UniProt accession number (SP AC),
                                and no matching protein is found, the editor will access an external server
                                (by default the EBI SRS server), to retrieve the corresponding protein.
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/editor/int-protein.png" title="" alt="Adding Proteins"/>
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                The orange colour bar on the left identfies new Proteins not
                                yet added to the Interaction. The first Protein is already part of the
                                Interaction and hence for absence of the color bar next to it. These
                                'color coded' Proteins do not form part of the current Interaction until
                                the user save them either by selecting 'Save' or 'Save &amp; Continue' button.
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                Any errors in adding Proteins are shown red colour as shown below.
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/editor/int-protein-error.png" title=""
                                     alt="Error in adding Proteins"/>
                                <br/>
                                <br/>

                                This section lists all the Features participating in the current
                                Interaction. A Feature can be added or edited by selecting 'Add Feature'
                                and 'Edit Feature' button respectively. The 'Edit Feature' only appears
                                if there is a Feature attached to the Protein.
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/editor/int-feature.png" title="" alt="Adding Features"/>
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                            </blockquote>

                        </section>
                        <!-- Proteins -->

                        <section title="Features" name="editor.int.features">

                            <blockquote>
                                <img src="./images/editor/new-feature.png" title="Feature Editor"
                                     alt="Feature Editor"/>
                            </blockquote>

                            <blockquote>
                                A Feature must contain at least a single Range and hence Ranges section is shown
                                in 'required field' colour. The following figure shows a Feature with
                                multiple Ranges.
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/editor/add-ranges.png" title="" alt="Adding Ranges"/>
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                The 'Create Undefined Feature' button provides an easier way to create a Feature
                                with an undefined range. The following figure shows the result of selecting this
                                button.
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/editor/feature-undefined.png" title="Undefined Feature"
                                     alt="Undefined Feature"/>
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/editor/warning.gif" title="" alt="" align="left"/>
                                However, you still need to select the CvFeatureType before submitting the form.
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/editor/feature-type-error.png" title="" alt="Missing CvFeatureType"/>
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                The 'Mutation' button switches the current view between Mutation/Normal
                                Feature editor.
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/editor/mutation-button.png" title="" alt="Mutation Button"/>
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/editor/warning.gif" title="" alt="" align="left"/>
                                You can switch back to the Normal Feature editor at anytime (or vice versa) but you
                                will lose data entered in the form.
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                The mutation editor as a result of switching from Normal to Mutation mode.
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/editor/hotspot-editor.png" title="" alt="Hotspot Editor"/>
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                See the curation manual for the format of hotspots. Any errors in adding hotspot entries
                                are shown in red with an error message.
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/editor/hotspot-error.png" title="" alt="Hotspot Error"/>
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/editor/warning.gif" title="" alt="" align="left"/>
                                There is no 'Save &amp; Continue' button. You need to save the data by selecting the
                                'Submit' button.
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                                <img src="./images/editor/idea.gif" title="" alt="" align="left"/>
                                The CvFeatureType defaults to hotspot. Ensure that the entire entry for hotspot
                                is complete before you select the 'Submit' button.
                                <br/>
                                <br/>
                            </blockquote>

                        </section>
                        <!-- Proteins -->

                    </section>
                    <!-- Interaction -->

                </section>
                <!-- Other Editors -->

                <section title="FAQ" name="editor.faq">

                    <blockquote>
                        <b>What browsers Editor supports?
                            <br/>
                        </b>
                        It has been tested using Mozilla (1.4 or above), Explorer (6.0),
                        Konqueror (2.1.1 or above) and firefox (1.0 or above). With the Konqueror it has been
                        noted that pop up windows do not get the focus (need to bring them manually). Also,
                        the footer is almost at the top when a page does not contain much
                        information.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>

                        <b>Do I need a JRE installed to run the Editor?</b>
                        <br/>
                        No, you don't need Java Runtime to run the Editor as it is designed to
                        run on thin clients (see the next question about JavaScript).
                        <br/>
                        <br/>

                        <b>Do I need JavaScript to run the Editor?</b>
                        <br/>
                        Yes. Some editors such as Experiment or Interaction wouldn't work if
                        Javascript is disabled. Links to search application wouldn't
                        work as well.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>

                        <b>I get a strange error with dispatchXXX not found?</b>
                        <br/>
                        This happens if you have disabled Javascript. Some forms use Javascript
                        to store values for the server to check. When Javascript is disabled, the server
                        throws an error as it can't find the parameter dispatchXXX.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>

                        <b>Do I need to logout when I am finished?</b>
                        <br/>
                        There is no need to logout because your session will timeout if it has
                        been inactive for 30 or more minutes. However, by explicitly logging out
                        you are releasing the resources (good thing to do). So, we recommend
                        explicit logouts.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>

                        <b>Can I connect to my last session when my session expires?</b>
                        <br/>
                        No. Once your session expires you need to login again and this in turn
                        will start a new session.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>


                        <b>Sometimes I get an error when Enter key is pressed for a search string in the sidebar.
                            <br/>
                        </b>
                        This behaviour was observed with Explorer and Konqueror but not
                        with Mozilla. The simple solution is to click on Search button instead.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>

                        <b>It hangs for a tax id in BioSource editor.</b>
                        <br/>
                        Either Newt server is not accessible or down. There is no way to get
                        around this problem; you need to access the Newt server to do the auto-completion.
                        <br/>
                        Currenlty, you
                        <u>have to</u>
                        go through Newt to get your taxid validated as well as the
                        shortlabel and the fullname set to the BioSource.

                        <br/>
                        <br/>

                        <b>The parameter to search for Proteins given as name is ignored when a value is provided for
                            Intact Ac in the Interaction editor.</b>
                        <br/>
                        By default, IntAct AC is the most specific and it is followed by SP AC
                        and finally the shortlabel. Given two values for name and
                        IntAct AC, the latter is always given the priority.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>

                        <b>In the interaction form, is there a way to save or delete all Proteins in one single
                            click?</b>
                        <br/>
                        Not at the moment. We may add this behaviour later.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>

                        <b>The focus seems to be lost (can't enter or select an item in the editor).</b>
                        <br/>
                        This is most likely due to the search popup having the focus. Close the search
                        popup window to regain the focus.
                    </blockquote>

                </section>
                <!-- FAQ -->

            </section>
            <!-- Editor -->


            <section title="hierarchView" name="hierarchView">

                <blockquote>
                    HierarchView is a web based application which allow to visualise interaction networks contained in
                    IntAct.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>
                    This includes :
                    <ul>
                        <li>Query interface: to select the set of Interactors from which the interaction network is
                            built,</li>
                        <li>Visualising an interaction network as a two dimensional graph,</li>
                        <li>Visualisation of a protein's context (using the
                            <a href="#search">Search application</a>
                            ),
                        </li>
                        <li>Performing action by clicking on a protein of the displayed network, to</li>
                        <ul>
                            <li>Center the view,</li>
                            <li>Extend the view,</li>
                        </ul>
                        <li>Displaying GO terms of all proteins from which the interaction network is built,</li>
                        <li>Displaying the GO hierarchy of a selected GO term</li>
                        <li>Highlighting all proteins annotated by a specific GO term (selected by the user)</li>
                    </ul>
                </blockquote>


                <section title="Graphical user interface" name="hierarchView.GUI">

                    <blockquote>
                        The graphical user interface integrates:
                        <p>
                            <u>a sidebar</u>
                            <blockquote>
                                <p>
                                    <u>the basic sidebar</u>
                                    :
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    Some components of the sidebar are always visible whatever the state of the
                                    application.
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    This includes:
                                    <ul>
                                        <li>on the top, the query interface.</li>
                                        <li>on the bottom, a set of IntAct related links.</li>
                                    </ul>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    <u>the advanced sidebar</u>
                                    :
                                    After loading a first interaction network, more features are available in the
                                    sidebar :
                                    <ul>
                                        <li>below the query interface, the
                                            <i>Graph</i>
                                            menu which allows to expand and
                                            contract the current interaction network,
                                        </li>
                                        <li>above the link section, the mouse-click behaviour section which allows the
                                            user to
                                            switch the mouse-click behaviour either to center the view or add a new
                                            network.</li>
                                    </ul>
                                </p>
                            </blockquote>
                        </p>

                        <p>
                            <u>a content frame</u>
                            <blockquote>
                                <p>
                                    <u>header</u>
                                    : specifies from which protein(s) the current interaction network is built
                                    as well as the number of nodes and edges. If needed, the selected GO term used for
                                    the
                                    highlight is displayed.
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    <u>protein interaction network</u>
                                    : a clickable image representing the requested interaction network.
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    <u>highlight top panel</u>
                                    : a list of all GO terms associated with proteins in the currently displayed
                                    interaction network.
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    <u>highlight bottom panel</u>
                                    : After selecting one of the GO term displayed in the top right frame,
                                    the related GO hierarchy is displayed, allowing the user to perform a highlight by
                                    selecting the GO term of the hierarchy.
                                </p>
                            </blockquote>
                        </p>

                        <center>
                            <table border="0">
                                <tr>
                                    <td>
                                        <a href="./images/hierarchView/PPIN.png" target="_blank">
                                            <img src="./images/hierarchView/PPIN-small.png" border="0" width="300"
                                                 height="197"></img>
                                        </a>
                                    </td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>click the image to enlarge</td>
                                </tr>
                            </table>
                        </center>
                    </blockquote>

                </section>
                <!-- GUI -->


                <section title="What is an interaction network ?" name="hierarchView.PPIN">

                    <blockquote>
                        It is a graphical way of representing a protein protein interaction network as
                        a two dimensional graph structure. Within that graph, the nodes represent proteins
                        and the edges represent interactions.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        The entry point of an interaction network is an
                        <b>Interactor</b>
                        (either
                        <b>Protein</b>
                        or
                        <b>Interaction</b>
                        ) around which we will look for all Interactors within a specified
                        threshold called depth. A depth 1 would be all direct Interactors of the selected protein.
                    </blockquote>

                </section>
                <!-- What is an interaction network ? -->


                <section title="How to display an interaction network ?" name="hierarchView.display">

                    <blockquote>
                        Type in the
                        <i>Interactor</i>
                        form either a protein name or accession number and
                        click the
                        <i>search</i>
                        button to display the related interaction network. You are free
                        to type a comma separated list of proteins in order to display all of them in one go.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        The visualization systems shows all specified proteins with a bold font. As soon as the
                        interaction network is displayed, the user interface is changing slightly to offer more
                        interactivity.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        When querying IntAct to display an interaction network, if the query is ambiguous (e.g.
                        the query
                        <i>snu*</i>
                        could describes several proteins such as snu66, snu13...),
                        you will be automatically forwarded to the search application where you will be able to
                        select the targeted protein(s).
                    </blockquote>

                </section>
                <!-- How to display an interaction network ? -->


                <section title="How to interact with the interaction network ?" name="hierarchView.PPIN.interact">

                    <section title="Add a further interaction network" name="hierarchView.PPIN.add">

                        <blockquote>
                            When adding an interaction network, a new one is generated according to the user's wishes
                            and then merged with the current one.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            There are two ways of adding additional interactors to the displayed interaction network:
                            <ul>
                                <li>
                                    Type in the
                                    <i>Interactor</i>
                                    form either a protein name or AC and click
                                    the
                                    <i>add</i>
                                    button. You are free to type a comma separated list of
                                    protein in order to display all of them in one go.
                                </li>

                                <li>
                                    If the protein of interest is available in the current interaction network, you
                                    can switch the mouse-click (sidebar) behaviour to
                                    <i>add a network</i>
                                    then click
                                    on the wanted protein.
                                </li>
                            </ul>
                        </blockquote>

                    </section>
                    <!-- Add a further interaction network -->


                    <section title="Center the view" name="hierarchView.PPIN.center">

                        <blockquote>
                            In order to navigate in the interaction network, you can decide to change the current
                            central protein. To do so, switch the mouse-click (sidebar) behaviour to
                            <i>center the view</i>
                            , then, click on the wanted protein. The current interaction
                            network will be reloaded as the interaction network of the selected protein.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            Bear in mind that it would have had the same effect to type the name or accession
                            number of the protein in the
                            <i>Interactor</i>
                            form and click on the
                            <i>search</i>
                            button.
                        </blockquote>

                    </section>
                    <!-- Center the view -->


                    <section title="Expand the current interaction network" name="hierarchView.PPIN.expand">

                        <blockquote>
                            In order to improve the readability and the loading time, the default depth of an
                            interaction network has been set relatively low. Nevertheless you can increase that
                            parameter in order to expand the current interaction network by clicking the
                            <i>expand</i>
                            button in the sidebar. Bear in mind that there is a minimum and maximum depth, this
                            implies the
                            <i>expand</i>
                            (
                            <i>contract</i>
                            ) button disappears when the maximum (minimum)
                            depth is reached.
                        </blockquote>

                    </section>
                    <!-- Expand the current interaction network -->


                    <section title="Highlight the interaction network" name="hierarchView.PPIN.highlight">
                        <blockquote>
                            After loading an interaction network, a list of GO terms specific to the set of selected
                            proteins is displayed in the top right frame of hierarchView. By clicking on one of them,
                            the related GO hierarchy appears in the bottom right frame (powered by
                            <a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ego" target="_blank">QuickGo</a>
                            ).
                            If a single GO term is found, the hierarchy is displayed automatically.
                            Now you can select one of the displayed GO terms of the hierarchy in order to highlight
                            in the interaction network all proteins annotated with that GO term in IntAct.
                            These proteins will appear with a differently colored label.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            In the displayed hierarchy, the lower GO term is the more specific, and the higher you go,
                            the more generic the GO terms become. Bear in mind that when selecting a GO term in the
                            displayed hierarchy the highlight is done with a set of GO terms including the selected one
                            and all its children (i.e. until the most specific).
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            <center>
                                <table border="0">
                                    <tr>
                                        <td>
                                            <a href="./images/hierarchView/highlight.png" target="_blank">
                                                <img src="./images/hierarchView/highlight-small.png" border="0"
                                                     width="299" height="197"></img>
                                            </a>
                                        </td>
                                    </tr>
                                    <tr>
                                        <td>click the image to enlarge</td>
                                    </tr>
                                </table>
                            </center>
                        </blockquote>

                    </section>
                    <!-- Highlight the interaction network -->


                    <section title="Retreive the interaction network in PSI MI XML format"
                             name="hierarchView.PPIN.download">
                        <blockquote>
                            After loading an interaction network, you can request to download its representation in
                            PSI MI XML format. To do so, you have to click on the
                            <i>Download</i>
                            button of the
                            <i>PSI-XML</i>
                            section and a new window will appear in which the XML content will be
                            displayed. After the data are fully loaded you can save that content on your hard disk.
                            <br/>
                            <u>Note to Netscape's users</u>
                            : You may have to right-click and select
                            <b>view source</b>
                            in order to display the XML code.
                            <br/>
                            <br/>
                            You can then, for instance, load the downloaded data in an external tool for further
                            analysis.
                            <br/>
                            You can find a list of the tools supporting the PSI MI XML format
                            <a href="http://psidev.sourceforge.net/mi/xml/doc/user" target="_blank">here</a>
                            in the
                            <i>Tools</i>
                            section.
                        </blockquote>

                    </section>
                    <!-- interaction network download -->

                </section>
                <!-- How to interact -->

            </section>
            <!-- hierarchView -->


            <section name="mine" title="MiNe - Minimal connecting network">
                <blockquote>
                    MiNe is a web based application which computes the minimal connecting network for a given
                    set of proteins if possible.
                    <br/>
                    A minimal network is a sub network of an interaction network which has to fulfill the following
                    points:
                    <ul>
                        <li>it has to contain all wanted proteins</li>
                        <li>the sum of the weight of the edges has to be minimal.
                            <br/>
                            The weight of the edges can be either different or identical (e.g. weight 1) -
                            then the minimal connecting network is actually the network with the minimal number of nodes
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                    <br/>
                    This includes :
                    <ul>
                        <li>Query interface: to select the set of
                            <i>Interactors</i>
                            from which the minimal network is computed,
                        </li>
                        <li>Computation of the minimal connecting network,</li>
                        <li>Forwarding to HierarchView to visualise the network</li>
                    </ul>
                </blockquote>

                <section name="mine.search" title="How to search for a minimal connecting network ?">
                    <blockquote>
                        Type in the
                        <i>Interactor</i>
                        form either a protein name or accession number and
                        click the
                        <i>Find network</i>
                        button to get the related minimal connecting network.
                        You are free to type a comma separated list of proteins in order to display all of them in one
                        go.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        As search phrases can be used:
                        <ol>
                            <li>IntAct Ac: EBI-44444</li>
                            <li>Gene names: lsm7</li>
                            <li>UniProtKB Ac: Q08162</li>
                            <li>UniProtKB Id: rr44_yeast</li>
                            <li>InterPro Ac: IPR001900</li>
                            <li>GO Id: GO:0000176</li>
                        </ol>
                    </blockquote>
                </section>

                <section name="mine.ambiguous.result" title="What is an ambiguous result ?">
                    <blockquote>
                        If your search returns an ambiguous result all found proteins for every search phrase
                        are shown on this page.
                        <br/>
                        An ambiguous result occurs when you search for either an
                        <i>Interaction</i>
                        or an
                        <i>Experiment</i>
                        or at least one search phrase returns more than one protein.
                        <br/>
                        To proceed you have to select the proteins from which you want to compute the minimal connecting
                        network by activating the checkboxes related to the proteins.
                    </blockquote>
                </section>

                <section name="mine.ambiguous.additional" title="What are additional search phrases ?">
                    <blockquote>
                        In this textbox you can enter an additional search query that will be used to complement the set
                        of proteins currently shown on the page.
                        <br/>
                        If you want to add search phrases to your selection type a protein or an accession
                        number or a comma seperated list into this field
                        <br/>
                        If you want to search for the phrases instead of the selection make sure to deselect
                        all proteins found by the previous search.
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        Please be aware of the search limit of seven proteins !
                    </blockquote>
                </section>
            </section>


            <section name="graph2mif" title="Graph2MIF -  Export IntAct to PSI Molecular Interaction Format">
                <section name="graph2mif.overview" title="Overview">
                    <blockquote>
                        This application exports a graph as PSI MI Format (MIF).
                        The user can access this using the SOAP protocol as a WebService, Servlet or direct.
                    </blockquote>
                </section>


                <section name="graph2mif.access" title="Access">
                    <blockquote>
                        The URL to access the web service is the following:
                        <pre>http://server.domain[:port]/intact/graph2mif</pre>
                        <br/>
                        You can replace
                        <code>server.domain[:port]</code>
                        by
                        <code>www.ebi.ac.uk</code>
                        <br/>
                        <br/>
                        For validation: Just call the URL above within a browser.
                        It should displays a basic web form which allows to fill in the parameters of your query.
                        <br/>
                        There are two ways to request a MIF:
                        <ul>
                            <li>Soap: Using a SOAPClient. The only method you have to call is
                                <code>http://server.domain:port/intact/graph2mif/soap/getMIF(ac,depth,striftmif)</code>
                                .
                            </li>

                            <li>Direct URL call:
                                <code>http://server.domain:port/intact/graph2mif/getXML?ac=
                                    <i>Ac</i>
                                    &amp;depth=
                                    <i>Integer</i>
                                    &amp;strict=
                                    <i>(true|false)</i>
                                </code>

                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </blockquote>
                </section>


                <section name="graph2mif.usage" title="Usage">
                    <blockquote>
                        Depending on the way you would like to access the data you call the soap-method
                        <pre>getMIF()</pre>
                        or directly the URL like mentioned above.
                        Both of them have three Arguments
                        <pre>ac, depth, strictmif</pre>
                        A graph will be retrieved (representing a protein protein interaction network)
                        starting with an interactor of
                        <pre>ac</pre>
                        and expanded to depth of
                        <pre>depth</pre>
                        <pre>striftmif</pre>
                        is a Boolean. When set to true, a graph in PSI MI XML format will only be generated if the data
                        allows to provide all required PSI MI attributes. Otherwise a exception is thrown.
                        When set to false, the generated graph will still be in PSI MI format, but might lack some
                        mandatory elements.
                        <br/>
                        The resulting graph will be returned in PSI MI XML as a formated XML-String.
                        <br/>
                    </blockquote>


                    <section name="graph2mif.usage.wsclient" title="Example webservice client">
                        <blockquote>
                            The example java webservice client
                            <i>Graph2MIFWSClient</i>
                            is also included in this package.
                            <br/>
                            The client must know where to access the WebService, so go to the source code and change the
                            Line with
                            <code>URL url = new URL("...")</code>
                            to your system. Afterwards you can compile it using
                            <i>ant client"</i>
                            .
                            <br/>
                            Just call:
                            <code>java uk.ac.ebi.intact.application.graph2MIF.Graph2MIFWSClient
                                <i>ac</i>
                                <i>depth</i>
                                <i>(true|false)</i>
                            </code>
                            to get a graph of IntAct as MIF. The result will be printed to
                            <i>STDOUT</i>
                            .
                            Have a look at the simple source code for getting an impression of how to write your own
                            client.
                        </blockquote>
                    </section>


                    <section name="graph2mif.usage.console" title="Example console client">
                        <blockquote>
                            This client does not implement a WebService, it directly accesses the IntAct Database.
                            The rest is mainly the same:
                            <code>java uk.ac.ebi.intact.application.graph2MIF.Graph2MIFClient
                                <i>ac</i>
                                <i>depth</i>
                                <i>(true|false)</i>
                            </code>
                            to get a graph in PSI MI XML format. The result will be printed to
                            <i>STDOUT</i>
                            .
                            Have also a look at the simple source code for getting an impression of how to write your
                            own client.
                        </blockquote>
                    </section>
                </section>
                <section name="graph2mif.references" title="PSI Molecular Interaction Format">
                    <blockquote>
                        <ul>
                            For details about the mapping have a look at the annotated
                            <a href="graph2MIF/MIF-1.23-annotated.xsd">MIF.xsd</a>
                            or
                            at the generated mapping documentation
                            <a href="graph2MIF/mapping/graph2MIF.html">here.</a>
                        </ul>
                        <ul>
                            For details about MIF hava a look at the homepage of the PSI project:
                            <a href="http://psidev.sourceforge.net/">Proteomics Standards Initiative</a>
                        </ul>
                    </blockquote>
                </section>
            </section>
            <!-- end graph2MIF -->


            <section name="proviz" title="ProViz - Standalone Interaction Visualization System">
                <blockquote>
                    ProViz is a high-performance, standalone visualization system for molecular interactions. For a
                    detailed description,
                    please see the
                    <a href="proviz/proviz.html">ProViz user manual</a>
                    .
                </blockquote>
            </section>
            <!-- end ProViz -->

            <section name="targets" title="Targets - prediction of promising targets for pull-down experiments">
                <blockquote>
                    Uncovering the interactome is one of the primary challenges in the post-genomic era. The topology
                    information gained from the coverage of interaction space can shed light on the likely function and
                    structure of proteins within the network (Vitkup et al, 2001). Here we present a list of the 'best
                    baits' which give the highest return on experimental effort - i.e. those proteins which form 'hubs'
                    in the interaction network. These lists are generated using the Pay-As-You-Go strategy (Lappe, M.
                    Holm, L.(2004) Nature Biotechnology 22, pp 98 - 103) which detects and prioritises those proteins
                    which have the highest likelihood of being hubs based on the current data within IntAct for various
                    species. To illustrate the experimental effort which could be saved by using the strategy
                    recommended here, take the Human interactome as an example. It is estimated that 50,000 experiments
                    would be required to cover the entire human interactome following a purely random strategy for the
                    selection of targets. The information gain here is close to linear for each experiment. This could
                    be drastically reduced to less than 10,000 for 90% coverage of the entire human interactome by using
                    the proteins listed here as baits. This would save years of experimental effort. This of course
                    relies on the timely deposition of experimental data into the IntAct database in order that the
                    Pay-As-You-Go algorithm should be fully uptodate and effective.
                </blockquote>
            </section>
            <!-- end targets -->
        </section>
        <!-- applications -->

    </division>

</page>
